Hi and welcome back to another episode
with it's Dr. Dan and today we're going
to be looking at the law of partial
pressures. So the law of partial
pressure was originally made by Dalton
which essentially states that if I have
a bunch of individual gases that are all
in the same container. So I have all
these different gases. So if I take the
individual pressures of each gas and I
add them all together, it will be the
sum of the total pressure. So what that
kind of boils down to is a law that
looks very very similar to this one. So
we have P total, which is all gases in
your container plus the first gas, the
second gas, third gas and so on. So this
is just telling you pressure of an
indicy meaning as infinite number of
gases that you could possibly want in
your problem. So we just simply add them
all up. So kind of the idea is let's say
if I blow into a balloon and I blow air
into that. Well, air that's coming out
of you is going to be what you're
exhaling. So it's going to be CO2,
possibly some oxygen, nitrogen, the
mixture of trace gases that are going to
be in the air. So let's take a look at
air and try to get an idea of how we can
do a sample problem of this using this
formula. So if I say that I have a
sample of air and it has a volume of 19
L and it contains approximately
78% nitrogen, 22% oxygen,
and I'm telling you the temperature of
this sample is 28° C. Determine the
total pressure of each gas. All right,
so percents. Oof, these are always
really, really hard and a little scary
whenever we have anything with percents.
So whenever we have a percent problem,
the one thing we got to remember is the
word percent. So telling you that it's
out of 100 and we can represent this as
many different things as we want,
whatever units. So in this case being
that if you know 78 and 22, it equals
100. So that seems to be pretty
convenient for ourselves. So what we can
essentially do is oh if I have 78%
of nitrogen that's the same thing as
saying that oh I have 78 g of nitrogen
by mass in 100 g sample of air. So it's
a percent. So we can do that for
nitrogen and we can also do that for
oxygen as well. Well, okay. So if I have
both of those, well, what is something
that's really useful to convert to when
we have mass? Well, what's always our
goal in terms of a lot of our different
calculations? So, one thing you're going
to hear me say in a lot of different
videos on this channel is the goal is
the mole. Meaning that if we can convert
to moles, we can solve for almost
anything, which makes it really
exciting. So, when it comes to
chemistry, our goal is always the mole.
So, how do we get to moles with a mass?
Well, that always revolves around using
molar mass. So what we have to do is
look up our mar mass using our periodic
tables for both nitrogen gas and oxygen
gas. So let's first start with nitrogen.
So we have 78 g of nitrogen. We're going
to set up a tea table for ourselves. And
if you look at your periodic table,
you'll see one element of nitrogen is 14
g per mole. We have two of them cuz it's
a diatomic. So, it's going to be a total
of 28 g of nitrogen for every 1 mole of
nitrogen. And once we do that, we can
see, oh, g cancels g, leaving us with
only with moles.
So, when we only have moles here, well,
all right, that's very, very useful for
ourselves. We can convert that. So once
I do that math, so 78 / 28, you will get
2.79
moles of nitrogen. All right, that's
some that's something. Now let's do the
same thing for oxygen. Well, for oxygen,
I also have 22.0 g of oxygen. We'll set
up a table for ourselves. And when we
add up two oxygen atoms, that's a total
of 32 g from our periodic table of O2
for every 1 mole of O2.
I'll do the same math. So 22 / 32. And
what we are going to get is 0.688
moles of O2 for our species. Now why
what can we do with that from here
though? We were given a couple other
things. We had temperature. We're trying
to we had volume. So let's maybe
highlight those. So we had a volume. We
had a temperature. Then we're trying to
find total pressure. So from all those
pieces,
it doesn't mention any change is
occurring. It's just saying that there
is a current system that there isn't
anything going on that's different here.
Um, so whenever that's the case, when
we're looking at a current state of a
gas, that's the ideal gas law. And the
whole idea of Dalton's law is that all
gases are very, very tiny
indistinguishable particles, meaning
that they are all just little orbs
wandering around in constant random
motion. So if I take our moles of
oxygen, our moles of nitrogen, and let's
say I combine them into our container,
right? So that's our sample gas. That
makes a bear. If I throw them both in
there, can you tell the difference? Can
you pick out the little nitrogen? If you
look around your room right now and I
start looking around, can you start
picking out all the different atoms?
Well, no. So what does that exactly tell
us? Well, if you kind of think of that
in terms of pressures,
we can simply add them together to get
total. But what else does that relate
to? Well, that also relates to moles.
Oh, that's something that's that's
something that's very powerful. So if
that relates to moles, one thing that we
can have now is a new formula where the
total number of moles is equal to n1 +
n2 plus as many gases as you have. So
another partial law comes into play
which is partial moles. So being that
that's the case, what we can do with
that, let me just add another page here.
is we can use that to do more
calculations. So if I take my moles
which from earlier
I can find out what my moles of my total
moles in my sample are. So if we take
the moles of oxygen the moles of
nitrogen so meaning we'll take 0.688
moles and we'll add it to 0.279 279
moles or not 279
2.79 moles of nitrogen.
We'll add those together and what we're
going to end up getting is the total
moles of gas that's in this sample. So
just indistinguishable particles that
are in my sample. So why is that
important? Well, we want to know what
the total pressure is, which is related
to the total number of moles. So, now we
can take all of the values that we had
earlier, plug them into the ideal gas
law for pressure. So, let's write down
our ideal gas law equation. So, ideal
gas law is PV is equal to NRT. We want
to get pressure by itself. So we're
going to divide volume out from the
right hand side getting pressure alone.
We'll have our new equation which is
pressure is equal to nrt
div / volume. And now what we can now do
is plug in our values from before. We
have our number of moles which we just
calculated.
We have the ideal gas constant which is
something that is well known. we went
over in a previous video. So for us that
value is 0.08206
L atmospheres moles Kelvin.
We have our temperature which for us is
28° C. We have to convert that to
Kelvin. So that would just be plus 273.
Um so that'll come out to about 301
Kelvin.
Okay.
And then we'll divide that by the volume
of the gas, which was 19 L.
Okay. This is a long problem. A lot of
moving pieces as we're going through
this. So when we solve, we'll do 3.48
times our constant*
301. Solve it. Then divide by 19. Now,
when you do that, you're going to get a
total pressure of 4.52
atmospheres of gas. So, this is all the
gas that's in our sample. And that is
our final answer. Fantastic. That's
exactly what we want. Now, what else can
you do with this? Well, what if I asked
you what is the partial pressure of each
gas? Can we do that? Can we actually
figure out the individuals? Right? So,
being that this gas is essentially the
total gas is equal to the pressure of
uh of each of the gases combined. So, in
this case, it's P1 plus P2 aka nitrogen
and oxygen. Can we figure out the
individual gases? Well, we can. So, I'm
going to go into a little derivation for
ourselves. So something another skill of
how to use the combined gas law to for
different purposes and what this is
going to show is a new equation.
So in this sample that you have of air
temperature and volume are already
described and they're not changing. They
are in a constant state. But the same
thing can be said with moles and with
pressure as well.
Well, is that entirely true? Can we
define that maybe a little differently?
Well, we can. One thing that we could do
is is use the law of partial uh sorry,
use the law of the combined gas law.
Meaning if I take P1 V1 and I do the
expanded version so including moles so
P1 V1 N1 T1
and instead of me saying P2 V2 why don't
we instead say oh well we have the total
number of of pressure
the total volume
the total moles
and the total temperature. Well, the
thing about this is is temperature and
volume are constant. So when they are
constant, they end up canceling out
because they are not changing. And one,
if you remember from our original
problem, was a really tiny value. N
total was also very big. So that was
changing. So what this happens, what
happens is these go away. And as a
result it ends up giving us a completely
different and usable
law in a sense. So P1 N1 is equal to P2
N2 or sorry N total or P total N total.
And what we can go around from there is
we can try to rearrange this thing in a
sense where we can actually find and
utilize it to become not only this
equation but what it can eventually lead
to is is molar fractions.
So what do I mean by what is a molar
fraction? Well, if I rearrange this
equation
where I times both sides by n1.
So when I do that, n1 will be on the
left hand side
and I'll get n1 over n total times total
pressure.
This term here
you can commonly see in textbooks as the
letter kai which represents
the mo the molar fraction. So it's how
much fraction of gas is in your sample.
So with that all being said, how can we
figure out the partial pressures? Well,
we can use our our different amounts of
uh moles from our original problem.
So, in the very beginning in our first
one, so if I have let's say the partial
pressure of nitrogen,
well, we know the total amount of gas
was 4.52
atmospheres.
We and what we also know is we can see
how much uh the moles were. So the
individual moles were 2.79
moles
all over 3.48
moles. So what this is is the partial
divided by the total
times our total pressure. So this is P1
or sorry not P1 N1
all over N total
times total pressure.
So what we can actually get here is that
our partial pressure for nitrogen is
going to be 3.62 atmospheres
of N2. And we can do a very similar idea
with oxygen as well. We can take our
partial moles of oxygen and end up
plugging that into the equation too and
do the same type of calculation. So if
we take the 688 divide by 3.48
times it by the total pressure that is
there we can also get what the partial
pressure is of oxygen gas.
So this is something that is a very
powerful method. Lets you do partial
pressures, partial moles, everything all
in one equation.
So one last one. So if I have a very
common experiment.
So with this one, I have magnesium metal
and it reacts with hydrochloric acid.
This is something that's very commonly
done in most introductory chemistry
labs. In fact, you most likely did an
experiment like this this semester. So,
if magnesium metal reacts with
hydrochloric acid, what's going to
happen is the magnesium metal that we
have in here, it's going to be reacting
with all that HCl. When that happens,
hydrogen gas is going to be created.
It's going to displace all of this water
that's in the tube. So, this is being
collected over water at 26° C.
So, one thing about this, this is at
atmospheric pressure, which is at about
758 mm of mercury. I want you to
determine the mass of H2 collected. So,
how can we do that? Well, here's an
agenda for oursel. We are given a lot of
different pieces of information. We have
the volume of hydrogen gas. We have the
temperature of the water. We also have
the atmospheric pressure.
as well as a partial pressure. So what
are we trying to do? Well, we want to
determine what the mass of H2 is. So how
can we do that? How can we go from all
of this to everything here? Well, the
goal is always the mole. So how can we
try to get to moles in this case to
solve for the mass of hydrogen? Well,
we're given a total pressure and we're
also given a partial pressure. So, the
first thing we're going to use is
Dalton's law. So, why don't we start
there on our agenda? So, if I have my
total pressure, which in this case is
atmospheres,
this is going to be equal to the
pressure of the H2 gas being created and
the water vapor that is coming off as
well. So they're both existing in the
solution. So if my total pressure was
mm of mercury, we don't know the
pressure of hydrogen, but we were given
the pressure of
of uh water. So what we can do with
this, we can rearrange this and find the
pressure of hydrogen. So if we do that,
we'll get pH2
which is 758 mm of mercury minus 24 mm
of mercury.
So once we solve for that, essentially
what we're going to be getting is that
pressure. So with that being all done,
we're going to get about 734
mm of mercury of H2. Okay, so we just
did step one. Step two says let's
convert it to moles. So we were given a
bunch of different values. We have a
volume which was 482
ml. We have a temperature which was 26°
C. Um we don't have moles.
We do have an R constant. So we can
solve for the ideal gas law. So why
don't we use it? So PV= NRT is the
bridge. So once we are doing that, what
we need to do is rearrange it to solve
for moles. And in this case, it's going
to be moles of H2 in particular.
So what we'll do is we'll divide both
sides by RT.
This will get moles by itself.
So we'll have NH2
with PV
/ RT.
We'll plug in our partial pressure of
mercury. So that' be 734
millm of mercury. But the thing is, is
that in the correct units? So we got to
check that R
is 0.08206
um
lers atmospheres moles Kelvin. So is are
all of our units correct? Well none of
them are correct. So the first thing we
need to do is convert everything. So
let's do the first one. So pressure. So
pressure is in 734 mm of mercury. So how
do we convert that to atmospheres? Well,
760 mm of mercury
is one atmosphere.
So what what this will do is cancel out
millime of mercury.
And this will allow us to get
atmospheres, which is 0.966
atmospheres once you divide those two
numbers.
volume is going to be when you're taking
um the value we had earlier which was
482 millilit.
So 482 mls we got to convert that to
lers. So 1,00 ml is 1 liter
millilit cancels that will give us 0.482
L.
Temperature
it was 26° C. We'll add 273 to that.
That'll give us 299
Kelvin. Okay, now we can plug all these
values in. So with that being said,
we'll plug everything in. So we have the
atmospheres,
we have our volume,
we have our R constant which is 0.08206
and then we also had our temperature
299K.
Once that is solved, this will give us
our moles of nitrogen.
So NH2
and what we will get is 0.0 01897
moles of H2.
Now, are we finished? Well, our last
step was to convert it to mass. How can
we get to mass? Molar mass, right? We
got our goal, which was the mole. Once
you get there, you can convert it to
anything you need. So, in this case, to
molar mass by using H2's mass. So, we'll
take our moles
of H2.
And what we're going to do is cancel out
moles
with the molar mass of hydrogen. So when
you take two hydrogen atoms from your
periodic table, multiply 1
* 2, that'll give you 2.016 g of
hydrogen. And what that's going to tell
you is that in your
tube from your experiment, you got
0.0383
g of hydrogen collected. And that is an
extremely
tiny value that you collected.
So that was a very involved problem that
went from you converting that did uh
moles partial pressures it that had all
of it in one problem. So partial
pressures are something that can be very
very applicable to many situations and I
wanted to cover all the bases. So
hopefully this video will help you on
future homeworks on concepts to study
for exams. Um so I try not to hold back
on harder problems here. So, I hope this
helps. Uh, let me know in the in the
comments what you thought. And if you
want anything else in the future, please
hit that like and subscribe button. And
thank you so much for listening and and
just being here to support. I'll see you
all later and have a wonderful rest of
your day. Bye now.
[Music]